A Guide to the Russell V. Bowers Collection
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Russell V. Bowers Collection 1940-1976
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
91/May/11
0.25 linear ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Mrs. Joanne Bowers.
Biographical/Historical Information
Russell Vernon Bowers was born 20 April, 1915 in Canton, Georgia. His father, a railroad worker, was transferred between several towns in Virginia during Bowers' early years. He received his BS from Lynchburg College in 1937 and a MS in biochemistry from the Medical College of Virginia in 1939. He then became a research assistant at the Department of Biochemistry at the University of Virginia in 1940.
During World War II, Bowers was commissioned a Captain and served in the Army at the Edgewood Arsenal, now part of the Aberdeen Proving Grounds. This Arsenal specialized in chemical warfare. After the war, Bowers returned to the Medical College of Virginia, earning his MD in 1950. He settled in the Mechanicsville area where he served as a general practice doctor for over 37 years.
Bowers had the honor of being given a unique medical artifact. While visiting his son in England, Bowers was introduced to Dr. N.G. Heatley, a leader in the development of penicillin. Bowers was given one of the original penicillin culture vessels "as a gesture of scientific friendship." This vessel is now in the Smithsonian Institution.
Bowers had a love for History, especially concerning the Civil War and Medicine. He wrote several articles including histories on Sir William Osler, William Halsted, and the development of penicillin. Bowers was also active in the community and in politics. He served as a delegate to the 1960 Democratic National Convention and was a member of the Electoral College in 1964. Bowers was also instrumental in creating a student loan fund for Hanover County students who attend Virginia Commonwealth University.
Bowers died 06 Oct, 1990 at age 75. He is buried in Richmond, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The collection contains speeches, photographs, and secondary source research material on several subjects of historical interest for Bowers including the history of penicillin, William Osler and William Halsted. The collection does not include anything on Bowers' medical practice or his personal life.
Arrangement
Records are arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Speeches and Addresses
  - "William Halsted" (Box-folder 1.1)
  - "Penicillin: Discovery and Early Research" (Box-folder 1.2)
    Incomplete speech. Ends at page 8.
  - "April 20th, 1977" (Box-folder 1.3)
    Possibly written by N. Heatley of early penicillin research at Oxford
  - Oxford: It's Doctors and their Incomes (Box-folder 1.4)
- Research Material
  All material are reprints of published articles.
  - Sir William Osler (Box-folder 2.1)
    - The Great Physician (Box-folder 2.1)
      Reid, Edith. Oxford Press, 1939
    - Osler's Remains Rest Among His Books (Box-folder 2.1)
    - The Unveiling of the Oxford Memorial (Box-folder 2.1)
    - The Sir William Osler Memorial at Oxford (Box-folder 2.1)
    - Sir William Osler: Last Days (Box-folder 2.1)
    - Letter (Box-folder 2.1)
      Letter by Martha Hubbard concerning Revere Osler's library at the Stuart and Tutor Club.
    - Osler's Practice (Box-folder 2.1)
      Harrell, George
    - "Where Wilson was a Summer Boarder" (Box-folder 2.1)
    - Information regarding Osler's home (Box-folder 2.1)
  - William Halsted (Box-folder 2.2)
    General photocopies from a book, a biography of his life
  - Miscellaneous Research (Box-folder 2.3)
    Photocopies of several books
    - Surgery of War (Box-folder 2.3)
      Article on Alexander Fleming
    - Bertichte Der Deutschen Chemischen Gesellschaft (Box-folder 2.3)
      German language journal about penicillin
- Reprints of published articles
  All of the articles in this folder are reprints and secondary sources. In many cases they are photocopies.
  - "Chimborazo Hospital" (Box-folder 3.1)
    The history of the hospital. From the Confederate medical exhibit of the Civil War centennial.
  - Sir William Osler
    - "19th Century Medicine" Feb 1976 (Box-folder 3.2)
      Journal of the American Medical Association, Vol 235. No. 5
    - "Osler's English School" July, 1973 (Box-folder 3.2)
      Medical History, Vol. XVII No. 3
    - "The Men who Inspired Osler" Feb. 1972 (Box-folder 3.2)
      Southern Medical Journal, Vol. 65 No. 2.
    - "Medical Tributes to Sir William Osler and Their Medical Associations" Dec. 1989 (Box-folder 3.2)
      Journal of the American Medical Association, Vol 242 No. 26
    - "Did William Osler Have Carcinoma of the Lung?" 1974 (Box-folder 3.2)
      Chest, Vol. 66.
    - "Osler Centenary Celebration at Oxford" Jul. 1949 (Box-folder 3.2)
      The Lancet
    - "A Hitherto Unpublished Appreciation of Sir William Osler" 1977 (Box-folder 3.2)
      Johns Hopkins Medical Journal, 140
  - Richmond Academy of Medicine
    - Richmond Medical Journal Jan. 1866 (Box-folder 3.3)
      Photocopy of first edition.
    - "History of the Richmond Academy of Medicine" Oct. 1962 (Box-folder 3.3)
      Virginia Medical Monthly Vol. 89
  - History of Medicine
    - Catalogue of an Exhibition of Books on Medical, Surgery and Physiology 1947 (Box-folder 3.4)
      Bodleian Library, Oxford
    - Surgeons and Surgical Care of the Confederate States of America 1960 (Box-folder 3.4)
      Stark, R. New York, NY
    - "Some Highlighting in the History of Amputation Reflecting Lessons in Wound Healing" 1967 (Box-folder 3.4)
      Bulletin of the History of Medicine, Vol. XLI No. 2
    - University of Oxford Medical School, Prospectus of the Clinical School 1974 (Box-folder 3.4)
      Oxford Press
    - Dun's Library 1976 (Box-folder 3.4)
      Royal College of Physicians of Ireland
  - Miscellaneous
    - "Amino-ethyl Phosphoric Ester from Tumors" 1936 (Box-folder 3.5)
      The Biochemical Journal, Vol. XXX, No. 2
    - "Acute Adrenal Cortex Exhaustion and its Relationship to Shock" 1938 (Box-folder 3.5)
      The American Journal of Surgery, Vol. XL No. 3
    - "The Biochemical Behavior of Lead" Jan. 1940 (Box-folder 3.5)
      The Journal of Biological Chemistry, Vol. 132, No. 1
    - "Phosphatase Studies: The Hydrolysis of Amino-Ethylphosphate..." Feb. 1940 (Box-folder 3.5)
      The Journal of Biological Chemistry, Vol 132, No. 2
    - "Choline Metabolism" Feb. 1940 (Box-folder 3.5)
    - "The Clinical Application of the Hippuric Acid and the Prothrombin Tests" Mar. 1940 (Box-folder 3.5)
      American Journal of Clinical Pathology, Vol. 10 No. 3
    - "Recurrent Pneumoccic Meningitis Treated with Sulfapyridine" 1941 (Box-folder 3.5)
      Journal of the American Medical Association, Vol 116
    - "Alcohol Absorption From the Skin in Man" 1942 (Box-folder 3.5)
      Quarterly Journal of Studies on Alcohol, Vol. III, No. 1,
    - "Stingray Injuries" 1959 (Box-folder 3.5)
      Public Health Reports, Vol. 74, No.10
    - "Medical Intelligence" 1962 (Box-folder 3.5)
      New England Journal of Medicine, Vol. 266
- Clippings and Photographs
  - Clippings 1976 (Box-folder 4.1)
    - "Ceramic Vessel Held World's Medical Genie" 15 Jun, 1976 (Box-folder 4.1)
      Richmond Times Dispatch
    - "Penicillin Vessel to be Displayed at UVa" 28 July, 1976 (Box-folder 4.1)
      The Daily Progress
  - Photograph of Samuel Preston Moore 1880 (Box-folder 4.2)
  - Photographs (Box-folder 4.3)
    This folder contains various photographs of paintings of William Osler, George Bakeman, Halsted, Osler, and Relly, James Basil Bowers, and a group photograph where Bowers is on the front row, right.